A Guide to the William Francis Rhea Papers, 1899-1902
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Francis Rhea Papers, 1899-1902
Library of Virginia
41312
2.475 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 14 August 2002 from L. and T. Respess Books, Charlottesville, Virginia.
Biographical Information
William Francis Rhea was born 20 April 1858 in Washington County, Virginia. He attended rural and private schools, then graduated from King College in Bristol, Tennessee, in 1879. Rhea was admitted to the bar in 1879 and began practicing in Bristol, Virginia. Elected judge of the Washington County court in 1880, Rhea served until 1885 when he was elected to the Virginia State Senate. In 1888, he returned to Bristol and became judge of the city court. Resigning in 1895, Rhea returned to the practice of law. Rhea was elected to represent the 9th Congressional District in the United States House of Representatives in 1898 and served from 1899 to 1903. Rhea's elections as a Democrat to the House in 1898 and 1900 were unsuccessfully challenged by his Republican opponent James A. Walker (1832-1901). Rhea lost his relection bid in 1902 to Republican candidate Campbell Slemp (1839-1907). Rhea was appointed a member of the State Corporation Commission in 1908 and he moved to Richmond, Virginia. He retired from the SCC in 1925. Rhea married first Mary Chester Keebler (1859-1913) in December 1878 and they had three children. He married second Rosa Smith Turpin (1869-1936). Rhea died 23 March 1931 in Richmond and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1899-1902, of William Francis Rhea (1858-1931) of Washington County, Virginia, consisting of correspondence to and from Rhea while serving as United States Congressman for the 9th Congressional District located in Southwest Virginia. Papers cover a wide range of topics such as local, state, and national politics, including Rhea's contested elections in 1898 and 1900 against James A. Walker (1832-1901); the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1901-1902; and a range of requests from Rhea's constituents.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into the following series: Series I: General Correspondence, 1899-1902. Series II: Postal Service, 1899-1902. Series III: Agriculture, 1900-1902. Series IV: Employment Requests, 1901- 1902. Series V: Military, 1900-1902. Series VI: Pensions, 1899-1902. Series VII: Contested Election, 1900-1901. Series VIII: Miscellaneous.
Contents List
- General Correspondence 1899-1902. (Box 1)
  General Correspondence, 1899-1902, consists of letters and telegrams to and from Rhea concerning local, state, and national politics, including Rhea's contested elections to Congress in 1898 and 1900 and his opponent in those elections, James A. Walker (1832-1901); Rhea's selection as Democratic candidate for Congress in 1900 and 1902 by his district; requests for Rhea to support or oppose various legislation; requests for aid or employment; and other political issues. Papers also contain correspondence concerning the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1901-1902 and how it may affect elections; the Philippines Insurrection; the clean-up of the Clinch River, including requests for jobs on the project; a weather bureau station in Wytheville, Virginia; a request that a courthouse be built in Catlettsburg, Kentucky; and pension and relief claims, including a pension request from Rebecca Mayo, one of the four remaining lving Revolutionary war widows. Papers also include correspondence concerning property Rhea is interested in selling.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - General Correspondence, 1899. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, January-March 1900. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, April-May 1900. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, June-December 1900. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1901. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, January-April 1902. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Correspondence, May 1902. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General Correspondence, June-July 1902. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General Correspondence, August-November 1902. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General Correspondence envelopes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Postal Service 1899-1902. (Box 1-2)
  Postal Service, 1899-1902, contains correspondence to and from Rhea, his constituents, and officials in the United States Postmaster General's office concerning post offices, postmasters, postal routes, and postal carriers located within Rhea's congressional district in Southwest Virginia, asking for new post offices or routes; moving existing offices; changing existing routes; asking for employment as postmaster or mail carrier; or complaining about problems with offices, routes, or carriers. Includes Rhea's correspondence with Postmaster General's office regarding these requests and complaints. Papers also include references to Rhea's contested elections of 1898 and 1900, the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1901-1902, and other political matters. Papers include envelopes that contain information concerning the resolution of questions and requests.
  Arranged in subseries: Post offices; Postmasters; Mail Routes; Mail Carriers; Mail Miscellany.
  - Post Offices. (Box 1-2)
    Arranged alphabetically by county, then by locality within.
    - Bristol City, July 1901. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Buchanan County--Joe, February 1900-August 1901. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Dickenson County--between Festoon and Rock House (Russell County), October-November 1901. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Dickenson County--Kiser's Store (Corrie?), February-April 1901. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dickenson County--Sandlick, December 1901-March 1902. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Giles County--Wingo (New River), February 1901. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lee County--Delclisur, January-July 1902. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lee County--Jonesville (declined), June 1900. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lee County--Minn (declined), May 1900-January 1901. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Russell County--Blue Grass, November 1901-February 1902. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Scott County--Autumn, April-June 1901. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Scott County--Boozy, January 1902. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Scott County--Dora, March-May 1902. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Scott County--Flag Pond, March 1900. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Scott County--Jess, June 1900. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Scott County--Saratoga, May-September 1901. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Scott County--Sinks (Bruno), April-May 1902. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Tazewell County--Bandy, March-April 1902. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Tazewell County--Cedar Bluff, August 1900-January 1901. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Tazewell County--Ernest (Tiptop), November 1900-August 1901. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Tazewell County--Pocahontas (declined), March-July 1900. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Washington County--Clip (postmaster and removal), November-December 1900. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Washington County--Fleet, January-February 1901. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Washington County--Green Cove (declined), June 1900. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Washington County--Hazel Spring, November 1899-February 1900. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Washington County--Ketron, March-April 1901. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Washington County--Medina, July 1902. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Washington County--Stump, August 1901. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Wise County--Big Stone Gap, November 1901-March 1902. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Wise County--Bondtown, May-August 1902. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Wise County--Joplin, January-June 1901. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Wythe County--Buddle, June-July 1900. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Wythe County--Wytheville, June 1901-February 1902. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, December 1900-February 1901. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Postmasters. (Box 2)
    Arranged chronologically by County, then by locality within.
    - Giles County, March 1902. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Giles County--Pembroke (stolen mail), April 1901. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Lee County--Democrat, February 1902. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Pulaski County--Pulaski, December 1901-February 1902. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Pulaski County--Snowville, June 1901. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Russell County--Lebanon, February-March 1901. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Scott County--Boozy, July-November 1901. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Washington County--Abingdon (complaints), January 1902. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Wise County--Big Stone Gap, January 1901-January 1902. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Wythe County--Max Meadows, October-December 1901. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Mail Routes. (Box 2)
    - Buchanan County--Prater to Grundy, March-June 1901. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lee County--Gibson Station (Sunday mail), January-February 1901. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Lee County--to and from Rose Hill, January-March 1902. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Pulaski County--Newbern to Essie, February 1902. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Russell County--Cleveland to Hansonville, June-October 1901. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Russell County--Honaker to Davenport (Buchanan County), August-October 1901. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Russell County--Lebanon to Point Truth, January-March 1902. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Scott County--Snowflake to Fugate Hill (Russell County), January-February 1902. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Washington County--Greendale to Craig's Mill, August-September 1901. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Washington County--Medina to Green Cove, May-June 1902. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Wythe County--Wytheville to Bland (Bland County), January-March 1902. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Mail Carriers. (Box 2)
    Arranged alphabetically by individual.
    - Robert B. Devault--Clintwood (Dickenson County) to Coeburn (Wise County), February-August 1901. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - J. W. Ervin--Festoon (Dickenson County), September-December 1901. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - J. S. Lawson--Newport to Eggleston (Giles County), February-March 1901. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - John Price--Elk Garden (Russell County) to Saltville(Washington County), August-September 1901. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Mail Miscellany, January-May 1901. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, January-May 1901. (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Agriculture 1900-1902. (Box 3)
  Agriculture, 1900-1902, contains answers to an unidentified questionaire from various counties located in Rhea's congressional district. Series also includes Rhea's correspondence with the Department of Agriculture regarding his allotment of seeds which congressmen received annually, as well as requests from constituents for seeds, trees, and pamphlets concerning agriculture.
  - Correspondence, 1900. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1901. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, March-June 1902, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Agricultural reports from Southwest Virginia counties, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Employment Requests 1901-1902. (Box 3)
  Employment Requests, 1901-1902, consists of correspondence to Rhea containing requests from constituents regarding federal employment and Rhea's response that most positions required would-be applicants to take the Civil Service exam.
  - William B. Leslie, October 1901-January 1902. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Paul Sexton, February-December 1901. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - M. N. Shufflebarger, December 1901-January 1902. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mark L. Wallis, February 1901. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - A. S. J. Wheeler, November 1901-February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Military 1900-1902. (Box 3)
  Military, 1900-1902, includes correspondence to and from constituents, many serving in the military, asking for Rhea's help in securing commissions, promotions, transfers, discharges, and payment for service while in the military. Papers also contain a request for Rhea to intervene in a desertion case of a son of a constituent, as well as a request from a constituent for Rhea's assistance in helping him locate his son serving in the army in the Philippines.
  - Marion S. Battle--seeks commission in Army, February-March 1901. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - William W. Bentley--seeks commission in Army, September 1901-January 1902. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Charles M. Blackford--examination for appointment in Army, January 1902. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - E. Wirt Crockett--seeks commission in Army, March-April 1901. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - John W. Hyatt--seeks commission in Army, December 1901-January 1902. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - J. S. Kelly--attempting to locate his son in Army in Philippines, April-July 1902. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Frank Lewis--seeks transfer in Navy, April 1902. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - J. C. McNew and Abner McNew--seek payment for military service, February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - M. M. Mills--seeks to attend artillery school, July 1901. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Carson L. Perry--requests discharge from Army, December 1900-January 1901. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - R. K. Spiller--requests transfer/reinstatement in Army, February 1901-February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - L. Harry Strother--seeks appointment as major in adjutant-general's office, February-March 1901. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Smith G. Talbot--examination for appointment in Army, July 1901. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Robert Thompson--desertion from Army, February-April 1902. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - W. O. Trenor--seeks commission in Army, February-July 1901. (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Pensions 1899-1902. (Box 3)
  Pensions, 1899-1902, contains correspondence from constituents asking Rhea to assist them in securing pensions for Civil War and U.S. military veterans, or for relatives of soldiers killed during the Spanish- American War or the Philippines Insurrection.
  - William H. Burgis, September 1901-March 1902. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lizzie B. Crockett, mother of Allen T. Crockett, January-April 1902. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Jennie Dennis, mother of William E. Dennis, February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Lewis Hood, December 1900-March 1901. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Charles Hopper, November 1900-April 1902. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Mary Hopper, widow of Alexander Hopper (alias William Harper), December 1900-June 1901. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Matilda Mathews, mother of Andrew Johnson, August 1901. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Lucy Milligan, mother of [?] Mitchell[?], August 1900-January 1902. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lawrence E. Payne, December 1899-May 1901. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - William Pennington, January-February 1901. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Sarah J. Shell, widow of Henry B. Shell, November 1901-February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - [?] Snavely, February 1901. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - S. R. Timberlake, February 1901. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Jacob Wilcox, February 1902. (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Contested Election 1900-1902. (Box 4-5)
  Contested Election papers, 1900-1901, contain letters, depositions, voter lists, instructions, and other documents concerning Rhea's contested 1900 election against Republican James A. Walker. Letters include Rhea's correspondence with his legal representatives concerning his strategy, county election officials, and other interested parties in the counties making up the 9th Congressional District; and correspondence from election officials concerning Republicans who voted for the Democrat Rhea as opposed to Walker. Depositions include those from election officials in Pulaski, Smyth, and Washington Counties. Voter lists include voter party affiliation by precincts in Pulaski and Russell Counties, and by race in Bristol. Papers also include a county-by-county vote tally for the 1896 9th District congressional election of 1896 between James A. Walker and Samuel Walker Williams; Democratic campaign committee instructions to election officials; Democratic party canvass books and lists; a Minnesota state ballot; and a copy of the Baltimore (Maryland) AMERICAN, 5 November 1900, containing a sample ballot.
  Arranged alphabetically by county, followed by miscellaneous folders.
  - Bland County correspondence, January-February 1901. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bland County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bristol City correspondence, January-February 1901. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bristol City--voter lists by race. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bristol City--voter lists by race (marked). (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bristol City--voter list by race (white) (marked). (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Buchanan County correspondence, January-March 1901. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Buchanan County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Craig County correspondence, January-February 1901. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Dickenson County correspondence, January-November 1901. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Giles County correspondence, January-July 1901. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lee County correspondence, January 1901. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lee County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Pulaski County correspondence, January 1901. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pulaski County depositions, January 1901. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Pulaski County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pulaski County--voter lists by precinct. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Pulaski County--voter lists by precinct. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Russell County correspondence, December 1900-March 1901. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Russell County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Russell County--voter lists by precinct. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Scott County correspondence, December 1900-March 1901. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Scott County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Smyth County correspondence, January-March 1901. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Smyth County deposition (incomplete), 1901. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Smyth County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Tazewell County correspondence, December 1900-January 1901. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Tazewell County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Washington County correspondence and depositions, December 1900-February 1901. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Washington County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Wise County correspondence, December 1900-July 1901. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Wise County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wythe County correspondence, January-July 1901 (October 1902). (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Wythe County--Republicans voting for Rhea in 1900 election. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1896 congresional election results for Southwest Virginia. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Baltimore (Md.) American, 5 November 1900, newspaper containing sample ballot. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Minnesota ballot, 1900. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Instructions to election officials from the Democratic Campaign Committee. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Democratic Party canvass books and lists, 1900. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous (Box 5-6)
  Miscellaneous items include a handwritten and typewritten copy of a speech delivered by Rhea in the United States House of Representatives on 14 May 1902 on the United States occupation of the Philippines; two of three volumes containing materials relating to Rhea's contested 1898 election against James A. Walker for the 9th Congressional seat, published by the Government Printing Office, middle volume is missing; Democratic Campaign Book for the congressional election of 1902; and mailing addresses for Rhea as a member of Congress.
  - Speech, delivered 14 May 1902, by Rhea on the United States and the Philippines (typed). (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Speech, delivered 14 May 1902, by Rhea on the United States and the Philippines (handwritten). (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Contested Election Case of James A. Walker vs. William F. Rhea, volume 1, Government Printing Office, 1899. (Box 6)
  - Contested Election Case of James A. Walker vs. William F. Rhea, volume 3, Government Printing Office, 1899. (Box 6)
  - Democratic Campaign Book Congressional Election 1902 issued by the Democratic Congressional Committee. (Box 6)
  - Congressional mailing labels for William F. Rhea. (Box 6)